<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A voice from heaven, calling the people of God to a perfect separation from mystical Babylon as it was delivered in a sermon at Pauls before the Right Honorable the Lord Major and Aldermen of the city of London, on Novem. 5, 1653 / by William Strong ...</title>
            <author>Strong, William, d. 1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6012</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R686</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11944953</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11944953</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51309</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61852)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51309)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 516:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A voice from heaven, calling the people of God to a perfect separation from mystical Babylon as it was delivered in a sermon at Pauls before the Right Honorable the Lord Major and Aldermen of the city of London, on Novem. 5, 1653 / by William Strong ...</title>
                  <author>Strong, William, d. 1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert White for Francis Tyton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vyner, Thomas, --  Sir, 1588-1665.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XVIII, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:51309:1"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Viner</hi> Major.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Tueſday the eighth day of <hi>Nov.</hi> 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered that Mr. <hi>Strong</hi> be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired from this Court to Print his Sermon Preached at <hi>Pauls,</hi> on the fifth of this inſtant <hi>November.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sadler.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51309:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Voice from Heaven, CALLING The PEOPLE of GOD to a Perfect SEPARATION FROM Myſtical Babylon. AS it was delivered in a Sermon at <hi>Pauls</hi> before the Right Honorable the Lord Major and Aldermen of the City of <hi>London,</hi> on <hi>Novem.</hi> 5. 1653.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Strong,</hi> PREACHER of the GOSPEL at the ABBY WESTMINSTER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert White,</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> and are to ſold at the Sign of the three Daggers in Fleetſtreet, near the Inner Temple Gate. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51309:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51309:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable THOMAS VINER, Lord Maior of <hi>London,</hi> and the Right Worſhipful the Court of Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough there be many reaſons which might perſwade met ſilence, eſpecially at ſuch a time, in which ſome men are made <hi>Tranſgreſſors for a word,</hi> nay every word makes them Tranſgreſſors; and <hi>benè latere,</hi> wiſely to conceal a mans ſelf, ſpecially in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, is one great part of the wiſdom of this Age; Yet by your <hi>Command,</hi> and in obedience to your <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> I have adventured this Sermon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to publike view; which I confeſs I
<pb facs="tcp:51309:3"/> was the more eaſily induced to, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it tends to keep up the <hi>memorial</hi> of that antient mercy, which (I conceive) God would not have forgotten by us: as alſo becauſe (unto my grief) I hear, that its commonly whiſpered by many, that it was only plotted by King <hi>James,</hi> like to that of <hi>Gowries</hi> Conſpiracy, for ſome Politick end. But who ever ſhall look into the ſtory, as related by <hi>Thuanus,</hi> (ſurely no enemy to the Papiſts) ſhall ſee reaſon enough to conclude the ſtory moſt true, and the deſign on their part real; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De libertate conſcientia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> The occaſion he tells us, was a deep diſcontent, for not attaining a <hi>tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Religion;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sic a Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logis ſuis diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerebatur, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem deponere, &amp; regna con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere penes ſupremum Eccleſiae ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium eſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> that the Popiſh Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines had ſeveral Debates about it, to ſet the Conſciences of the Conſpirators free from their obedience and Allegiance: great <hi>Conſultations</hi> were held with forrein Princes, great aſsiſtances promiſed, perſons brought from ſeveral parts, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them related to the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and of that faction, to act in this deſign; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>E ſodalitio Jeſuitico machinatio ſanguinolenta, &amp; ſi fuiſſet per acta, ipſe ex animo &amp; intimis ſenſibus deteſtaturus erat. Et tam atrox &amp; immano faci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s Catholicos ſuſcepiſſe plus morte ſibi dolere.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:51309:3"/> as appears in the confeſsion of <hi>Garnet,</hi> who did acknowledge when he came to die, that the thing was ſo horrid, that it grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him more then death it ſelf, that the Catholicks ſhould have a hand therein. And yet will men who cry out againſt Antichriſt, plead ſo much for him, as to make this a feigned ſtory, and by this means make all our former praiſes to be mockings of God, and taking his name in vain, and bring the guilt of the blood of all the Conſpirators upon this Nation. But whither will ignorance and intereſt carry men? even to deſpiſe the mercies of God, Condemn the practiſes of the Godly, juſtify the wicked, and for ſome petty end, take part with their greateſt enemies.</p>
            <p>In this Sermon, warning is given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people of God againſt Poperie, which may ſeem to ſome men altogether needleſs; a melancholy conceit, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, eſpecially in ſuch a time as this, when we ſeem to be ſo zealous in departing from Antichriſt, that we are ready to go too far the contrary way; and
<pb facs="tcp:51309:4"/> to forſake the things of Chriſt, under the name of Antichriſtian. But I have read of a Woolf in Sheeps clothing; and do never look upon Satan as a roaring Lyon, more then when transformed into an Angel, and do never fear Antichriſt more, then when he profeſſes to fight under Chriſts banner. But in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture we have variety of Notes by which Antichriſt is deſcribed, and by theſe we ſhall beſt judge who are Antichriſtian <hi>in their</hi> Spirits, Principles, and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Antichriſt</hi> came in with an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy; when men fell away from God, the way of truth and Holyneſs, which <hi>before they</hi> profeſſed. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.</p>
            <p>2. He brought in a <hi>Lye</hi> in Doctrine and worſhip, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11. and that even in <hi>fundamentals;</hi> Antichriſt <hi>denying the Father and the Son,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.22.</p>
            <p>3. Antichriſt did impoſe upon all men under the danger of perſecution; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Papalem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</hi> Mede</note> he did <hi>make all, ſmall and great, rich and poor, bond and free, to receive his mark, and no man might buy and ſell</hi> (trade with him in
<pb facs="tcp:51309:4"/> things ſpiritual) <hi>that received it not,</hi> Revel. 13.16,17.</p>
            <p>4. He ſpeaks <hi>Blaſphemie</hi> againſt the Saints of God, and their worſhip; he blaſphemes the <hi>Tabernacle of God, and them that dwell in Heaven,</hi> Rev. 13.6. And there hath not been an age ſince the <hi>myſterie of iniquitie</hi> began to work, wherein more of theſe notes were to be found, then in that wherein we live; if therefore the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Antichriſt in theſe great things prevail ſo much among us, and yet we cry out even againſt the things of Chriſt as <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> it may juſtly make men fear that this is the decoy, the great deceit being to bring in Antichriſt under the colour of oppoſing him, and being zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous againſt him.</p>
            <p>And though we have cauſe to fear the effectual working of this deceit in all parts of this Nation, yet who ſees not that the great plot is upon this City? by reaſon of its <hi>confluence</hi> from, and its <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence</hi> upon all parts of the Nation: here they ſhall be favoured, followed, of what opinion ſo ever they be: its your
<pb facs="tcp:51309:5"/> duty therefore <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it with the more watchful eye: take care of theſe <hi>wanderers, wandering Stars</hi> the Scripture calls them, that have no fixed places, that have various motions; now they are here, but if you look for them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anon they are to be found in ſome other part of the Heavens: theſe are the men that raiſe Stirs, cauſe Tumults, make Factions, to that end that they may ſwim in ſuch troubled waters, and ſeem ſomebody in a Partie; who if they ſtood ſingle, would be wholly inconſiderable. Theſe prove <hi>ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers</hi> alſo, and whom they can not, dare not oppoſe, they dare aſperſe, <note place="margin">Jer. 20.10.</note> 
               <hi>Report ſay they, &amp; we will report it;</hi> this is but the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of evil. Such are to be noted by you, diſcountenanced, warned; and ſo much the rather, becauſe all the diſturbances that are among us, are becauſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as Clouds are carryed about with ſuch winds; if we could allay the winds, the Heavens would be clear; We ſpeak much of ſettlement; the beſt way to ſettle men is to remove thoſe that unſettle them; and to eſtabliſh them, is to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance
<pb facs="tcp:51309:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> thoſe whoſe buſineſs is to beguile unſtable Souls, that they may <hi>make merchandize</hi> of them. And when in this work it ſhall be told you, that it belongs not to you to meddle with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; your power is only in things Civil, being a Civil Magiſtrate; Do you conſider, the foundation of <hi>honeſty</hi> is laid in <hi>Godlineſs;</hi> and all the duties of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, are grounded in the obedience of the firſt Table. That men are to obey you for conſcience ſake, and conſcience reſpects God only; and if you ſet their conſciences at liberty in the things of God <hi>ſinfully,</hi> you may expect that God ſhall let their conſciences looſe from obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto you, <hi>judicially;</hi> for furely they that are to obey you only out of <hi>conſcience to God,</hi> if they make no conſcience of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to him, it cannot be rationally expected, that they ſhould be conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in obedience towards you. The Magiſtrate is to <hi>rule with God;</hi> and his great care is to be, that nothing provoke God to depart from his Government; for (what ever men imagine) it is the <hi>Lord
<pb facs="tcp:51309:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> that builds the houſe, that keeps the City:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 10.2.</note> and fire <hi>taken off the Altar,</hi> burns more fiercely, when ſcattered over the City, then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fire. Let therefore the great things of Chriſt, and of his Goſpel be your care, and be you very vigilant againſt all the wiles of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> for he is <hi>a Beaſt iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Earth,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 13.11.</note> of a baſe original, and yet growing up inſenſibly; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stirpium more.</hi> Mede.</note> and his <hi>horns are like a Lamb,</hi> when he ſpeaks <hi>like a Dragon.</hi> The more ſubtilty there is in this Adverſary, the greater circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is required in you. So ſhall you be choſen Inſtruments in the Lords hand, to keep this people from returning to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon;</hi> ſo ſhall you eminently ſerve your Generation, lay down your ſword in peace; and the ruine intended, endeavor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon this City, ſhall not be in your hands, which is the humble and hearty prayers of him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to ſerve you in the Goſpel, VV. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51309:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Voice from Heaven,</hi> Calling the People of God to a perfect ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from myſtical BABYLON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>REV. 18.4.</bibl>
                  <p>And I heard another voice from Heaven, ſaying, Come out of her my People, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Book ſets forth the ſtate of the Church, and of the Empire under the two laſt heads of the fourth Beaſt: and it contains in it, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Empire, three great Propheſies.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the <hi>Seals,</hi> which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive refer unto <hi>Rome</hi> Pagan.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Of the <hi>Trumpets,</hi> which refer unto <hi>Rome</hi> Chriſtian, after the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperour.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Of the <hi>Vials,</hi> which refer unto <hi>Rome</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian, after the Apoſtaſie ſpoken of 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3. <hi>There muſt come a falling away firſt, that the man of ſin
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51309:7"/> may be revealed, the ſon of perdition:</hi> the riſe of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is ſet down in this Book, <hi>Ch.</hi> 13. under the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of two Beaſts, noting his double power; one <hi>temporal;</hi> ſo he is a <hi>Beaſt ariſing out of the Sea with ſeven heads and ten horns:</hi> The other <hi>Eccleſiaſtical:</hi> ſo he is a <hi>Beaſt ariſing out of the Earth, having two horns like a Lamb, &amp;c.</hi> and his ruin is deſcribed <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. where are ſet down the ſeveral ſteps and degrees thereof.</p>
            <p>Theſe words of the Text refer unto the time of the <hi>fifth Vial,</hi> which is to be poured out upon the <hi>Throne of the Beaſt, Chap.</hi> 16.10. which in this Chapter is more fully ſet forth, with the manner, and the ſeveral circumſtances thereof; <hi>when a mighty Angel ſhall cry with a ſtrong voice, ſaying,</hi> Babylon <hi>the great is fallen, is fallen, and is become the habitation of Devils, and the hold of every foul ſpirit, and the cage of every unclean and hateful bird.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words now read unto you, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quamobrem aliquot Electi deliteſcunt adbuc in elu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vione Romanae impietatis, quorum Deus meminit in communi per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditione im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proborum.</hi> Bright.</note> are taken out of Jer. 51.45. <hi>My people, go ye out of the midſt of her, and deliver ye every man his own ſoul from the fierce anger of the Lord;</hi> and they contain in them two things firſt, An exhortation unto the people of God, who are yet ſuppoſed to be mixt amongſt the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Idolaters; yea even then when <hi>Rome</hi> comes to receive its laſt plagues; in theſe words, <hi>come out of her my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>The reaſon</hi> given thereof, taken from a double evil; Firſt of ſin, <hi>that ye be not partakers of her ſins;</hi> Secondly of ſuffering, <hi>that ye receive not of her plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two things are to be ſpoken of by way of explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, before I can propoſe the Doctrine which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend: and they are theſe, Firſt, <hi>What is meant here by</hi> Babylon.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51309:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>What is the deſtruction which is here threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto</hi> Babylon.</p>
            <p>Firſt, what is meant by <hi>Babylon;</hi> for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thereof, we read Chap. 17. ver. 3, 4, 5. <hi>Of a woman ſitting upon a ſcarlet coloured Beaſt, full of names of Blaſphemy,</hi> &amp;c. and her name was written in her forehead, Babylon <hi>the great, the Mother of Harlots; Babylon</hi> therefore here ſpoken of, is deſcribed to be a Woman: and verſ. 18. the Woman is interpreted to be <hi>that great City which reigneth over the Kings of the Earth;</hi> ſo that <hi>Babylon</hi> in the ſenſe of the holy Ghoſt, is a great City: and that antient <hi>Babylon</hi> cannot be here meant, is plain: partly, becauſe the ruin thereof was propheſied, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 21.9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.64. <hi>Thus ſhall</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon <hi>ſink, and ſhall not ariſe from the evil that I will bring upon her.</hi> Which threatnings were inflicted long before Saint <hi>Johns</hi> time: but the City here ſpoken of did then raign over the <hi>Kings of the Earth:</hi> and <hi>John</hi> in this book doth ſpeak of nothing but the things that were, and that ſhould come to paſs hereafter: as appears Chap. 1.19. <hi>Write the things which thou haſt ſeen: the things which are, and the things which ſhall be hereafter;</hi> It appears alſo, becauſe the Spirit of God hath given us two words of purpoſe to keep us off from a literal ſenſe; one, Chap. 11.8. which is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſpiritually called Sodom and Egypt:</hi> it is a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty therefore that is here ſpoken of, that hath the name of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet not to be literally, but ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually underſtood: and the other is Chap. 17.5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Myſterie, Babylon the Great:</hi> it is not therefore to be literally, but myſtically interpreted: and what City in S. <hi>Johns</hi> time did rule over the Kings of the Earth, but <hi>Rome?</hi> called every where in this Book <hi>the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51309:8"/> great City,</hi> and by Hiſtorians <hi>Orbis totius compendium: &amp; orbis terrarum lux &amp; regina, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cum caput illud O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccidet &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>eſſe cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit, quis dubitet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſe jam fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem rebu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> humanis or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bique terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: Illa eſt enim civitas, quae adhuc ſuſtentat omnia, &amp;c. Ne Tyrannus lumen illud effodiat, cujus interitu mundus ipſe lapſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus eſt,</hi> Lactan. de divin. praem. lib. 7. cap. 25.</note> Yea, and <hi>A Lapide</hi> himſelf, though a Jeſuit, doth acknowledge all this to be meant of <hi>Rome,</hi> and can be underſtood of nothing elſe: only he refers it to <hi>Rome</hi> in the latter dayes of the world: his <hi>Obſervation</hi> upon Chap. 18. is this, <hi>Nota, Romam meretricem eſſe, &amp; mercatricem, &amp; cauponam, quae vine ſuo omnes inebriat &amp; dementat.</hi> And this is called myſtically <hi>Babylon,</hi> upon a double account.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe of their reſemblance in ſin: Firſt in <hi>pride and Self exaltation: Babylon the glory of Kingdoms, the Beauty of the</hi> caldeans <hi>excellency,</hi> Iſa. 13.19. So <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe ſaith in her heart. <hi>I ſit as a Queen, and am no widow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow.</hi> Revel. 18.7.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In <hi>Tyranny and cruelty: Babylon hath been a golden cup in the Lords hand, that made all the Earth drunken; the Nations have drunk of her wine; therefore are the Nations mad.</hi> Jer. 51.7. So myſtical <hi>Babylon is a woman that ſits upon many waters, rides upon the Scarlet coloured Beaſt, and hath a golden cup in her hand, and ſhe was found drunk with the blood of the Saints, and the Martyrs of Jeſus,</hi> Rev. 17.6.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In their <hi>Witchcraft and Sorcery;</hi> therefore <hi>Caldeans</hi> and <hi>Southſayers</hi> are commonly put one for another: moſt of them being Magicians, and addicted unto thoſe unlawfull Arts: So <hi>Myſtical Babylon;</hi> by her Sorceries are <hi>all Nations deceived,</hi> Rev. 18.23. Which ſometimes makes me fear Popery in <hi>England</hi> much the more, becauſe it cannot but be apparent unto every ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious man, that <hi>Sorcerie</hi> grows common amongſt us:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51309:8"/> and we have many inſtances, that <hi>as Hereſie and Cruelty, ſo Hereſie and Sorcery have gone together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It is called <hi>Babylon,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>likneſs in the</hi> puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Vengeance upon Babylon, was the Vengeance of the Temple,</hi> Jer. 50.28. the Violence done <hi>to me and to my fleſh be upon Babylon, ſhall the inhabitants of Sion ſay; and my blood upon the inhabitants of</hi> Caldea, <hi>ſhall</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem ſay, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.35. So it ſhall be with Myſtical <hi>Babylon;</hi> in her was found the blood of of the <hi>Prophets, and of the Saints, and of all that were ſlain upon the Earth;</hi> and the Lord will avenge this blood of his ſervants at her hand, and will <hi>give them blood to drink, for they are worthy,</hi> Rev. 16.18. &amp; 19.2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The deſtruction of <hi>Babylon</hi> did come <hi>ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly;</hi> theſe <hi>two things ſhall come to thee in a moment, in one day, the loſs of children and widdowhood, they ſhall come upon thee in their perfection, in the multitude of thy Sorceries, and the great abundance of thy Inchantments;</hi> Iſa. 47.9. So will the Lord deal with myſtical <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> ſhe ſhall <hi>drink of the wine of the wrath of God which is poured out without mixture into the Cup of his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> her plagues ſhall come in <hi>one day: Death, and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>famine:</hi> and ſhe ſhall be <hi>utterly burnt with fire: For ſtrong is the Lord God who judgeth her,</hi> Rev. 11.10. &amp; 18.8.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The deſtruction of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall be <hi>perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual:</hi> it ſhall never <hi>be built, never be inhabited, nor dwelt in from Generation to Generation, but the wild Beaſts of the Deſart ſhall lie there,</hi> Owls <hi>ſhall dwell there, and</hi> Satyrs <hi>dance there,</hi> Iſa. 13.20,21. The ſame is ſaid of myſtical <hi>Babylon</hi> alſo: <hi>No crafts-man ſhall be found any more in thee, the ſound of the Milſtone ſhall be heard no more in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51309:9"/> thee, the light of the candle ſhall ſhine no more in thee, but thou ſhalt become the habitation of Devils, and the cage of every unclean and hateful Bird:</hi> Rev. 18.2.22,23.</p>
            <p>Secondly what is the deſtruction threatned to Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Babylon</hi> in this Book? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Duplex Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonis interitus in hiſce va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiniis, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo pro urbe Beſtiae regia, puta urbe Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana; dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de pro Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aut Civitate Romana quam conſtituit Papa,</hi> &amp;c. Mede clavis Apoc. Cap. 11.</note> there is a double ruin &amp; over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw denounced againſt her: Firſt, as Babylon <hi>is taken for the City</hi> called the <hi>Throne of the Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13.2. <hi>ſc.</hi> that which was unto the Heathen Emperours the Metropolis or Imperial City, this was given to this new Beaſt, and becomes his Throne alſo. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Babylon</hi> is to be deſtroyed under the fifth vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10. and unto this deſtruction the words of the Text refer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Babylon</hi> is not only taken for the City, but the <hi>Citizens,</hi> the inhabitants thereof; the chief part of which are the Pope, Cardinals, Biſhops, with their ſeveral Religious Orders, who after the burning of the City by the ten Kings, ſhall eſcape by flight, and ſhall ſend forth their Emiſſaries unto the <hi>Kings of the Earth,</hi> not ſubdued by the Lamb, and ſhall prevail with them to joyn in the ſame intereſt, and ſtir them up to unite in that great Battail <hi>Armageddon,</hi> where Antichriſt with all his ſcattered troups, and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, even all the wicked of the Earth, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed at once; for the Lord loves to ſee them pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh together, <hi>to bind them in bundles to burn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This deſtruction of <hi>Babylon</hi> is reſerved to the laſt Vial, that upon the Ayr; and then ſhall <hi>great</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon <hi>come up into remembrance</hi> before God to her ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruin, that her name ſhall either be blotted out, or become <hi>a Curſe in</hi> the Earth.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51309:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Having thus opened the words, the Obſervation which I have pitcht upon, is this,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Doctr.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That it is a ſpecial duty which the Lord requires of his people, living in ſuch times, that they make a ſeparation from Myſtical</hi> Babylon, <hi>and that eſpecially when her ruin draws near.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening of it, there are two things to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, What ſeparation is required.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, What are the grounds and the reaſons of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, What kind of ſeparation doth the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of his people? this we are the more narrowly to look into; becauſe it is a controverſie between us and them; and the queſtion, as Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> propoſeth it, is, <hi>Liceatne à communione viſibilis Eccleſiae diſcedere?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cameron opuſc. miſcel. pag.</hi> 522.</note> therefore I muſt give you this diſtinction.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>There is a ſeparation that is a ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>There is a ſeparation that is a duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>There is a ſeparation that is a ſin; Theſe are they that ſeparate themſelves, ſenſual, not having the Spirit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jude 19.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Decompound</hi> may ſeem to note thus much, that they ſeparate and ſeparate, till they have forſaken all the true Churches of Chriſt upon Earth; many there are for this kind of Separation, who ſay, there are no true Churches, Ordinances, Miniſtery, and with the foot of pride and contempt, not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from them all, but kick at them.</p>
            <p>Unto theſe I would only ſay three things; <hi>Firſt,</hi> this Doctrine doth at once deſtroy the whole plot of this Book of the Revelation, wherein the Lord ſhews unto <hi>John</hi> all things that ſhould be acted for his Church unto the end of the World; and the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors thereof, which are as the <hi>Chorus,</hi> and upon every
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51309:10"/> occaſion give their Acclamations, are the Churches.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Church is here meant, becauſe firſt there is Gods preſence amongſt his people, his Throne is there erected, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.3. ſutable to that, <hi>A glorious high Throne is the place of our Sanctuary,</hi> Jer. 17.12.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is Gods worſhip, Rev. 4.8. <hi>They reſt not day nor night, ſaying, Holy, Holy, Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It is a Church of men, not of Angels: for they ſing, thou haſt <hi>redeemed us to God by thy blood,</hi> Rev. 5.9. which cannot be ſpoken of the Angels.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is a Church of men upon Earth, and not in Heaven; for there are the ſeven ſpirits before the Throne, which notes the variety of the gifts and graces of the Spirit, which are proper only to the Earth: for in Heaven gifts ſhall ceaſe, as alſo the preſent manner of adminiſtration from the Throne.</p>
            <p>And there is before the Throne a <hi>Sea of glaſs,</hi> in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion to <hi>Solomons</hi> Sea, which was for the prieſts to waſh in, and that ſuppoſes defilement, which is not in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is a viſible, and not an inviſible Church: for here are <hi>Beaſts and Elders,</hi> which are Officers and Brethren, which belong only unto the Church vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: and they are deſcribed here as met together to give God glory, which belongs only to viſible Churches, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.9. <hi>And there be Angels round about the Throne, and the Beaſts, and Elders. Rev.</hi> 5.11. which ſhall not be in Heaven: for Chriſt ſhall put down <hi>all rule, and authority, and power,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.24. which is to be underſtood <hi>de principatu Angelico,</hi> as well as of any other power, and their ſhall be need of no ſuch guard in Heaven.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51309:10"/>
            <p>Fifthly, It is ſpoken of viſible Churches all the world over; for they ſay, <hi>Thou haſt redemed us by thy blood out of every Kinred, and Tongue, People and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and haſt made us unto our God Kings and Prieſts, and we ſhall raign in the Earth: Rev.</hi> 5.10. But they that maintain ſuch a ſeparation from all Churches, muſt blot out this Chapter out of their Bibles; for the pure times of the Church, its conceived, did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue above 360, or 365 years, and then <hi>The man of ſin</hi> began to be revealed: ſince which time this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion doth ſay, there have been neither <hi>Beaſts nor El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> to obſerve and give God the Glory of his act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, during the whole time of Antichriſts <hi>Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The Scripture doth clearly tell us, that during the whole time of this great apoſtacy of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, there are ſome that the Lord will preſerve pure unto himſelf, and which he will own as Churches during the whole time of Antichriſt: his firſt riſe is ſet forth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. and then we have the ſtate of the Church deſcribed, Chap. 14.1,2,3,4. by which it appears that when the whole <hi>world wondred after the</hi> Beaſt, yet there were reſerved <hi>an hundred forty and four thouſand, who ſtood with the Lamb upon Mount</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>having his Fathers Name,</hi> (not Antichriſts Mark) <hi>written in their forheads,</hi> and they ſung <hi>a new ſong,</hi> that is, did praiſe and worſhip God in an excellent and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable manner, which was hid from the reſt of the world who did worſhip the Beaſt: theſe are ſaid to be <hi>redeemed from amongst men, and were as the firſt fruits unto God, and to the Lamb,</hi> of that general Converſion which ſhall be when Antichriſt ſhall be deſtroyed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Canticum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum pro exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio. Pſal.</hi> 33.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. <hi>vel novum de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo beneficio liberationis factae Iſa.</hi> 42.10. <hi>vel no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum eſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatum, ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>And Chap. 15.1,2. we read of <hi>a ſea of Glaſs,</hi> upon which thoſe ſtood who had <hi>gotten the victory over the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51309:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> Beaſt, his Image Mark, and the Number of his name, &amp; they had the Harps of God in their hands;</hi> they did worſhip God purely and publikely, during the time of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts raign, which is commonly interpreted of the reformed Churches; And immediately after <hi>Babylons</hi> ruine, we read of the <hi>four Beaſts, and the four and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Elders,</hi> who obſerve this, and give the Lord the Glory, ſaying, <hi>Amen, Halelujah,</hi> Rev. 19.4. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore during the whole time of Antichriſt, there have been, and ſhall be ſome that are gathered into Bodies, members and Officers, <hi>Beaſts and Elders,</hi> owned as true Churches by Chriſt, who during the time of this Apoſtaſie, have <hi>kept their garments, are not defiled with women,</hi> but in reference to Antichriſts fornications, <hi>are Virgins, in whoſe mouth is found no guile, but they are without fault before the Throne of God;</hi> Rev. 14.4,5. How then ſhall any man ſay, that all Churches have been ſo corrupted by Antichriſt, as that they remain no more Churches unto Chriſt? when the Lord gives unto ſome of them this Teſtimony, that either they have not received <hi>the mark of the Beaſt,</hi> or have <hi>gotten the victory over it, and his Name,</hi> and the <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his Name,</hi> that is, whatſoever is Antichriſtian, and they remain as <hi>Virgins and without fault before his Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let all ſuch perſons conſider, that deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any true Churches of Chriſt, they muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty place themſelves in the Synagogue of Satan; which appears ſo much the more, becauſe they bring upon themſelves the guilt of the higheſt pride in the World, which was the Devils ſin; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. To unſaint a man is a great height of pride, much more to unchurch a Society, and that under the name of Antichriſtian,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51309:11"/> who profeſs to diſclaim Antichriſt, and whatſoever ſhall be made to appear to relate to him.</p>
            <p>But what is it then to deal thus with all the Churches of Chriſt upon Earth? Societies where the Lord hath manifeſted his preſence, to the Converſion and Salvation of many thouſand Souls, who have this Teſtimony from the Lord, that they have gotten the <hi>Victory over the Beaſt, his Image, his Mark, his Name,</hi> thoſe whom the Lord owns, as having his <hi>Name writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their foreheads:</hi> And yet to unchurch all theſe, and number them with the Antichriſtian Party to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, is ſuch a piece of Pride, as one would hardly have thought could have entred into the heart of any but the Devil; And that this is more immediatly from Satan, I am inclined to think, from a paſſage I have met with in <hi>Auſtin;</hi> When Satan could not prevail to keep the Chriſtian Religion out of the world, but the Goſpel did ſpread even as a Sun-beam among the Gentiles, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Euſeb.</note> he did then perſwade the Heathen, and they were confident of it, that the Chriſtian Religion ſhould continue in the world but three hundred ſixty and five years, and then they ſhould return to Paganiſm again; but that ſo long <hi>Peter</hi> had bewitched the world by his Sorceries, that they ſhould believe in Chriſt: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Definitum eſt quanto tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore manſura eſſet religio Chriſtiana: Petrum male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia ſubjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt, ut cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur Chriſti nomen per trecentos ſexaginta quin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> annos; deinde completo memorato numero annorum, fine mora ſinem ſumet.</hi> de civit. Dei. lib. 18. cap. 53.</note> happily by this Propheſie he might intend, that about this time Antichriſt, the man of Sin ſhould riſe, and the Temple of God be given <hi>to the Antichriſtian Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> (Popery being nothing elſe but <hi>Ethniciſmus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divivus</hi>) And ſo the Devils propheſie was after a ſort fulfilled, when after three hundred ſixty five years, or thereabouts, the apoſtacy of Antichriſt did over-ſpread
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51309:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> the World: But theſe men undertake to make it good, and that even in as large a ſenſe as Satan would have it underſtood; <hi>ſc.</hi> that there are no true Churches, no true Ordinances ſince that time; and ſo ſince Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts riſe, the Chriſtian Religion hath been deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or in a manner <hi>utterly</hi> baniſhed out of the world. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui fratres nullos extra ſuam partem agnoſcere vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebant, &amp; adverſus orbem terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſacrilegae diſſenſionis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare erexc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi> Auſt. de verit. Eccleſ. cap. 13.16.</note> There are another ſort, who, though they deny not all Churches as the former, yet like to the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> of old, they acknowledge none but their own, all other they readily term Antichriſtian, and ſuch as they can hold no Communion with, though they profeſs to believe the ſame principles of Religion, and walk in holineſs of Converſation: yet they deny them <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, as Churches,</hi> unleſs they come under their form. Now becauſe godly men may fall under this deluſion; therefore I deſire all ſuch perſons ſeriouſly to conſider theſe three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Chriſt in the days of his fleſh ſeparated not from the Church of the Jews, though there were abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and thoſe very groſs Corruptions in it: Now <hi>the Diſciple is not above his Lord;</hi> it is not good to make our ſelves wiſer or more holy then he.</p>
            <p>Secondly, When Chriſt holds communion as a head, we ſhould not deny it as members: Now Chriſt did not preſently give <hi>Babylon</hi> a Bill of Divorce, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption coming into that Church by degrees; and ſo long as Salvation was to be had, there this Voice was not heard from Heaven, <hi>Come out of her my people:</hi> they were not called to ſeparate from her Communion; and it muſt needs be dangerous for any perſon, to call a Society <hi>Loammi,</hi> which God hath not ſo named.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Where the Foundations of Religion are held, though there be many differences in circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51309:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> yet it is not lawfull to break communion with ſuch, much leſs under the name of Antichriſtian; For though the <hi>Sea of glaſs be mingled with fire,</hi> the <hi>fire</hi> of Contention, and though there be great differences in opinion, yet all may get the <hi>Victory over the Beaſt and his Image, his Mark, and his Name,</hi> and they may joyn together to praiſe God they have ſo, though it may be they are not all alike Victorious: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quas Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias non diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temur reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctionem &amp; communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem ſalutife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto capite &amp; fundamento ſanctae Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae Eccleſiae; cum illis decet nos re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinere frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionem.</hi> Daven. ad. hortat. ad pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Eccleſ. cap. 8.</note> This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath been a Rule given by Divines in ſeveral ages, for the reconciling of brethren among themſelves <hi>that hold the head,</hi> Keep to the Foundation, though in many things of leſs concernment they differ, and that is, that with all ſuch Communion is to be held, as with the Churches of Chriſt, their Errors not being ſuch as cut them off from Chriſt, or being inconſiſtent with Salvation. Upon this ground the antient Church did own the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> as brethren, and held it their duty ſo to do. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Optat. Mile. vit. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. <hi>de Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. Donat. Nomen fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruitatis non putavit iſtis denegandum; immo impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis eſſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavit de iſto nomine vel tacere.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Donatiſtas ab Orthodoxis pro fratribus agnoſci</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Fraternitatis nomen Donatiſtis faſtidioſum, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxis vero neceſſarium, &amp;c.</hi> For they durſt not deny Communion with them in Church Ordinances, whom they durſt not deny to enjoy Communion with Chriſt here, and of whom they could upon Scripture grounds hope they ſhould have Communion with them in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hereafter. And if this be not a Rule by which we ought to walk, there can be no Communion beetwen Parties diſagreeing in any thing: For ſo long as there is blindneſs in the mind of man, and ſome things in the Scripture <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>hard to be underſtood,</hi> ſo long as there are different degrees of light, and men not made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in love, 'tis impoſſible that in every thing we ſhould agree: Yet ſo long as we hold the main, that wherein Salvation lies (for <hi>in brevi &amp; facili ſtat
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51309:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> aeternitas: Hilar.</hi>) ſo long as we differ not in Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals, ſuch Doctrines which a man cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerves, <hi>ſine diſpendio promiſſae Salutis,</hi> without miſſing Salvation, this union in the great things of Religion ſhould ingage men to keep the <hi>unity of the Spirit</hi> in the <hi>bond of peace,</hi> and to take heed that they differ not in affections, where <hi>they cannot</hi> agree in opinion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>There is a ſeparation which is a duty; Come out from among them, and be you ſeparate,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.17. which is by <hi>Cameron</hi> and others ſaid to be double; <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſus internus &amp; externus,</hi> That is, a ſeparation from the <hi>corruption,</hi> and from the <hi>Communion</hi> of a Church.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is a <hi>ſeparation from the corruption</hi> of a Church; ſo we are to ſeparate in any Church in the world, that is, to abſtain from the evil thereof, and in our place to bear our Teſtimony againſt it: Thus we ſee, though the Lord Jeſus did hold communion with the Church of the Jews, ſaying, <hi>I will declare thy name unto my brethren, in the midſt of the Church will I ſing praiſe unto thee,</hi> Heb. 2.12. Yet he did ſeparate from all the Corruptions thereof, and was unto them a <hi>faithfull and true witneſs</hi> againſt their Erroneous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, Superſtitious Cuſtomes and Traditions: thus it was the duty of Gods people, from the firſt <hi>Working of the Myſterie of iniquity,</hi> to come out of <hi>Babylon;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> began their Teſtimony, as ſoon as <hi>Antichriſt</hi> began his Apoſtacie <hi>to tread down the Temple of God,</hi> or rather the outward Court thereof: For they Propheſied in <hi>ſackcloth and aſhes a thouſand two hundred and ſixty days,</hi> which is contemporary with the whole time of the Reign of Antichriſt, as appears, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2,3. But yet that was not an immediate
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51309:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſeparation <hi>from Communion;</hi> For the Church of God did a great while lie hid among them; There were <hi>tempora gemendi &amp; latendi,</hi> as <hi>Cameron</hi> ſpeaks, times of their mourning in, and groaning under thoſe corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions before a total ſeparation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is a time alſo when the Lord doth require a <hi>ſeparation from Communion;</hi> When his people are to withdraw all communion from ſuch, to look upon them as a Church of Chriſt no more, to abhor them in regard of Communion, as an accurſed thing: Thus when the Lord had given the Jews a bill of Divorce, and broke off the natural branches, which is not ſpoken of breaking men off from grace or electing love, <hi>for the Election obtained</hi> mercy, when the reſt were blinded; but it is here meant of being broken off from a Viſible Church ſtate, the <hi>good Olive tree</hi> being a type thereof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.24. When the Lord had thus called them <hi>Loammi,</hi> his people were to hold Communion with them as a Church no more, God having caſt them off, and <hi>wrath being come upon them to the uttermoſt:</hi> So though <hi>Rome</hi> were ſometimes a true Church of Chriſt, and afterward corrupted by degrees; yet when the Lord divorced her as an Harlot, as <hi>the Mother of Harlots,</hi> calls her <hi>Babylon,</hi> and not <hi>Sion,</hi> then it is the duty of his people, not only to ſeparate from their corruption as before, but from their communion alſo.</p>
            <p>I come now to give the <hi>reaſons</hi> of ſuch a ſeparation from Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> which are theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe God hath put her away, hath ſaid of them they are not my people, but <hi>ſpiritually</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Egypt, Antichriſtian Gentiles, <hi>ver.</hi> 11.2. when the Lord thus forſakes any people, we ſhould forſake
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51309:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> them; when the <hi>glory of the Lord</hi> departs from a people, the Angels withdraw their Protection, and by the ſame degrees, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 10.4,5.18.19. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.22.23. when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the <hi>glory of the Lord</hi> removed, the Cherubims alſo did lift <hi>up their wings;</hi> And as the departure of God is the ground of their withdrawing <hi>Protection,</hi> ſo it ſhould be of our withholding <hi>Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Such a ſeparation is to be made, becauſe in <hi>Babylon</hi> no Salvation can be had; <note place="margin">A Reprobate may in truth be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of all that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Religion of the Church of <hi>Rome. Eccleſia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè dicta non probat quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid probant mali Doctores admixti eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae, nec quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid boni Doctores haud bene docue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi> Melan. Daven. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort. cap. 4.</note> It was Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> his Obſervation long ſince, <hi>That a Papiſt by the Rules of his own Religion cannot go beyond a Reprobate;</hi> where Foundations are deſtroyed, Principles denyed, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and this not the Doctrine of ſome particular men only, (for ſuch there may be in the pureſt Churches of Chriſt upon Earth; as in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> there were thoſe that denyed the Reſurrection of the dead) but when it becomes the Doctrine of the Church, which they as a Church do profeſs to maintain, and refuſe to be reclaimed: then there is no <hi>more Salvation</hi> to be expected there; which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be the pouring out of the <hi>ſecond Vial</hi> upon Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> Rev. 16.3. <hi>The Sea then became as the blood of a dead man, and every living Soul died in the Sea:</hi> By the Sea is meant their Doctrine, and the Comprehenſion or Collection thereof: as by the <hi>Rivers</hi> are meant thoſe that carry abroad this Doctrine in all places and all parts of the World. This Doctrine is become <hi>the blood of a dead man, ex corrupta fit cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptiſsima;</hi> it was corrupt before, yet ſome lived in it; but now every <hi>living thing dyed:</hi> That is, there was no more Salvation to be had by the Doctrine of their Religion; therefore with them no more <hi>Communion</hi> is to be held.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51309:14"/>
            <p>Thirdly, We are to ſeparate from her, becauſe ſhe is become a perſecutor of all the people of God through the world: <hi>She rides upon a Scarlet coloured Beaſt:</hi> an Embleme both of Majeſty, and Cruelty: ſhe is <hi>drunk with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus, and in her will be found the blood of the Prophets, of the Saints, and of all that are ſlain upon the Earth,</hi> Rev. 18.24. A ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration therefore is a duty, that we hold not <hi>Communion</hi> with her, whoſe trade is Perſecution.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Gods people are to ſeparate from <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> becauſe God hath ſet himſelf againſt her to deſtroy her with a great and eminent deſtruction. For when ſhe comes up into remembrance before God, ſhe that made all Nations <hi>drunk with the cup of the wine of her Fornication,</hi> ſhall be made to drink of the cup of the <hi>wine of the fierceneſs of Gods wrath,</hi> Rev. 16.19. and ſhall with violence, as a <hi>Milſtone,</hi> be caſt into the Sea, and be found no more at all, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.19. It was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed long ago, <hi>That if any man worſhipped the Beaſt, or his Image, or received his Mark, he ſhould drink of the wine of the wrath of God without mixture, and be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with fire and brimſtone in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 14.10. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cujus vaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis &amp; confuſionis haec erit cauſa, quod Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num nomen, quo nunc re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur Orbis, tolletur è ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ, &amp; in Aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Imperi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>eveitetur, ac rurſus Oriens dominabitur, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Occidens ſerviet.</hi> de praem. divin. ſect. 7. cap. 15.</note> And this Judgement the Antients did foreſee, and do expect: <hi>Horret animus dicere: dicam tamen, quia futurum eſt, Romanum nomen de terra tolletur,</hi> Lactan. I am affraid to ſpeak it, yet I will ſpeak, becauſe it ſhall come to paſs, that the name of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall be blotted out, or taken away out of <hi>the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51309:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Fifthly, All Gods people are to ſeparate from her, that they <hi>partake not with her in her ſins;</hi> it hath been Antichriſts buſineſs from her very beginning to infect and corrupt others: and that ſhe doth after the manner <hi>of Harlots,</hi> in a way of Love, and in the moſt enticing manner: for ſhe gives the <hi>wine of her Fornication in a golden cup.</hi> This hath even been the manner of thoſe men, whoſe ſpirits Satan hath <hi>touched,</hi> from that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of devilliſhneſs left upon their ſpirits, to deſire and endeavor to draw others into fellowſhip with them in the ſame ſin, and the ſame condemnation: and as he that doth not reprove his brother, doth <hi>bear ſin for him,</hi> Lev. 19.17. So he that doth not give Teſtimony againſt ſin in that way which the Lord requires, brings upon himſelf the guilt thereof. It is not always enough to ſpeak againſt ſin, or to mourn for it, but a man is to ſeparate from them that walk in it; there is a time for <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom</hi> to vex his righteous ſoul from day to day: but there is a time when he muſt come out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> unleſs he will periſh with it.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, A ſeparation muſt be made, becauſe they that <hi>partake in their ſins, ſhall ſurely receive of her plagues,</hi> and God is no <hi>reſpecter of perſons,</hi> though ſuch as are juſtified, can never come under an eternal guilt: yet they may contract a temporal, which may involve them in the ſame temporal Judgements with the wicked, and ſo <hi>Sampſon like,</hi> they may die with the Uncircumciſed: <hi>The good Figs ſhall go into Captivity with the bad,</hi> though not to the ſame end, <hi>Jer.</hi> 24. If therefore Gods people deſire to be delivered from their plagues, they muſt not partake in their ſins, which they will alwayes do, until they forſake their Communion.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51309:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> Let this be unto all the people of God as a voice from Heaven, to perſwade them to come out of Myſtical <hi>Babylon:</hi> And the rather, becauſe the work of this day ſhould be, as to exalt God in this mercy and deliverance, ſo to make <hi>Popery</hi> odious ever after: therefore this day ſhould always revive our deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that being in our eye which <hi>Luther</hi> profeſſed to be his aim in all that he did, <hi>Brevi efficiam, ut anathema ſit, eſſe Papiſtam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we have the more need to be ſtirred up hereunto; becauſe ſince this Nation departed from <hi>Rome,</hi> there were never greater attempts, nor higher hopes to bring us back unto this ſpiritual <hi>Egypt,</hi> then there are at this day. To make this manifeſt, I ſhall propoſe to you ſome of my obſervations upon the preſent times, which ſeem to argue a tendency and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination this way.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>A Univerſal unſetling of all things in Religion:</hi> all the Principles, and the Doctrines of Godlineſs are either denied or diſputed, though it be true, <hi>Spiritus Sanctus Scepticus non eſt:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </note> which is to me a ground of fear that there is an intent to bring in <hi>another Goſpel,</hi> Antichriſts Goſpel, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>that lye;</hi> I dare not ſay, I dare not think that this is the intendment of all thoſe that go this way: but ſurely it is <hi>finis operis,</hi> though not <hi>operantis;</hi> Yet I am not without fear, that many do it deſignedly, and <hi>ſpeak lyes in hypocriſie</hi> to that very end: when we look upon the riſe of Antichriſt, we ſhall find that Satan before hand caſt out of <hi>his mouth a flood after the woman,</hi> which is interpreted to be the Arian hereſie, and abundance of corrupt Doctrines ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying it, which though they paſs too and fro for ſome years, yet all ſetled and were gathered into the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51309:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> at laſt; and it is to be feared Satan hath the ſame aim at this day, though Magiſtrates and men in Authority may profeſs never ſo much againſt it: <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratores facti ſunt Chriſtiani, ſed diabolus nondum factus eſt Chriſtianus.</hi> Auguſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Conſider the inſtruments that are abroad in the World;</hi> we read of <hi>frogs ſent out of the mouth of the Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 16.13. that is, by his eſpecial command and commiſſion; and theſe go forth unto the <hi>Kings of the Earth</hi> in all ſhapes; and we have cauſe to fear (nay ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent ground to believe) that beſides the men of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt minds riſen up among our ſelves, there are many of thoſe ſent in among us; it were well if we could look upon our Cities, Army, Navy, yea Councels to be free: and ſo much the rather it is to be feared, becauſe we ſee all antient Hereſies revived, <hi>Arians, Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Montaniſts, Patripaſsians,</hi> yea that conceit of <hi>Joachim Abbas,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joachim Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas <hi>docebat, triplicem do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinam à tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus perſonis dimanare; doctrinam, ſc. Legis à Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii quod con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignatum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus à Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio, tertiam doctrinam à Spiriu ſancto expectandam, quam appellat Evangelium aeternum.</hi> Daven. in Coloſ. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> that there is a Goſpel of the Spirit, another Goſpel then that preached by Chriſt and to obſerve by what mean perſons theſe doctrines are vented, and yet all the antient Arguments uſed to maintain them: A conſidering man obſerving this, can hardly imagine but that there be ſome that do ſecretly, and with the beſt advantage inſtil ſuch things into them, and that in an unobſerved way; for they are ſaid to be ſpirits, that is, though they act very pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfuly, yet inviſibly: their motions, ways and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are not known.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Conſider that conſtant preſsing of liberty of Conſcience,</hi> which if granted, muſt be univerſal; for who hath power to lay a reſtraint upon one mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51309:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> more then another? and therefore the Patrons of this opinion do plead for a toleration for Popery, upon a Religious account; and that it is no more to be impoſed upon, then any other perſwaſion: as alſo that doctrine of <hi>Mariana</hi> the Jeſuite, <note place="margin">Marian. c. 10. Cont. Volit. l 2. Cap. 16.</note> now ſo generally inſiſted upon, and pleaded for, <hi>Princeps nil ſtauat de Religione,</hi> The Magiſtrate is not to meddle with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion: there were two Doctrines antiently, which of neceſſity brought in Popery; though a man knew-nothing elſe of that Religion, <hi>ſc. That the true Church cannot err;</hi> and <hi>that the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is that true Church:</hi> Now there are two other principles ſprung up in the world; <hi>Firſt,</hi> that the word in the heart, and the Spirit working there, is not to be tryed and examined by the word in the Book, that being but a dead letter, and for the Spirit to be examined by the word, is a minoration thereunto.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as the word muſt not try the ſpirits of men, ſo Magiſtrates have nothing to do with their Religion. Theſe two principles received, lay all open to Popery or Atheiſm. And if Popery, as a Religion, receive but a Toleration, and the ſame Countenance that others do, (it being a Religion moſt agreeable to Nature, as corrupt, and ſo exactly fitted to it) it will ſoon have the moſt followers: for when Popery firſt appeared in the world, the <hi>whole world wondred after it,</hi> as it had done after Arianiſm <hi>a little</hi> before.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Look to the Apoſtacy</hi> of the preſent age, men falling from all things in Religion, and with an impudent face denying deriding all; the Scriptures, the Trinity, the Godhead of Chriſt, his ſufferings and ſatisfaction, Juſtification by imputed Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Law of God as the Rule of Obedience, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51309:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> whatſoever Doctrines Chriſtian Religion is built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: now we know that a great <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> did make way for <hi>Popery,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.3. <hi>God giving them up to believe a lye:</hi> and by this means <hi>the man of ſin,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the lawleſs one, was revealed; and there is great cauſe to fear, that the preſent Apoſtacy amongſt us may have ſuch a tendency: for we ſee men fall from one thing to another, untill they hold to nothing in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion: ſuch an <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> (as I think, I may without breach of Charity ſay) that hath not been the like in any Chriſtian Church, ſince that great Apoſtacy before named: and being thus become as it were an <hi>outward Court,</hi> may we not fear that God ſhould give us over to be trodden down of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Gentiles again? and not receiving truth in the love of it, he ſhould give us up to believe <hi>that lye?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, If we conſider farther, that Antichriſt ſhall have yet a day for it, the time of the <hi>killing of the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> being yet to come: For they muſt <hi>Propheſie in ſackcloth and aſhes, a thouſand two hundred and ſixty daies,</hi> which is Contemporary with the whole reign of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, which is <hi>two and forty months;</hi> and if we take the beginning from the diviſion of the Empire into ten Kingdoms, <hi>The ten Kings receiving Power the ſame hour with the Beaſt,</hi> I cannot find upon any account, the time of their Propheſie in <hi>Sackcloth and Aſhes</hi> to be fulfilled: and if ſo, their killing time, and the inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Antichriſtian party over their dead bodies, becauſe <hi>they were dead that tormented thoſe that dwell on the Earth,</hi> muſt be yet to come, and that neer unto the time of Antichriſts ruine; and who knows? yea hath not every one reaſon to fear that the preſent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51309:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> Apoſtacy and defection may lay the ground of, and prepare the ſpirits of men for ſuch <hi>a Perſecution?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>What means elſe that general</hi> revolting unto the Doctrines of Popery, and Arminianiſm? The ſpirits of Popery, which the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> (being the Popes Janizaries) have laboured moſt in, and had great conteſts with the <hi>Dominicans</hi> about them, before ever the name of <hi>Arminius</hi> was heard of in the world: and that they are <hi>Symbolical,</hi> and the paſſage eaſie from one to the other, the examples of <hi>Bertius, Tilenus, Vorſtius,</hi> and many others do make manifeſt: But we need not go abroad for inſtances: We ſaw in Epiſcopal times, that thoſe that were moſt forward in receiving and propagating theſe Doctrines of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> they ſoon fell into the ſuperſtitions of <hi>Rome,</hi> in all their ways of Worſhip: and we have reaſon to expect that it ſhould be ſo in our time alſo: Thoſe Doctrines being as infectious now, as they have been in times paſt.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>What may a man think of that general endeavor that there is to take off the odium from Popery and Papiſts among us?</hi> That courting of them, aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, and complying with them; ſo that with too many a Papiſt finds more favor then a faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel: Nay, what means that general neglect of the obſervation of this day, <hi>In perpetuam Pontificiorum ignominiam?</hi> Nay, why is it denyed by ſome, and the Religious obſervance thereof, as if it were not a thing <hi>plotted by them, but rather fained</hi> by us?</p>
            <p>Eighthly, <hi>What is the meaning of that deſign now on foot againſt the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance?</hi> both being ſo clearly laid down in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51309:18"/> and the latter having been ſo fully proved by the Law: Is it not to be feared that all this is, becauſe they are the men that are lookt upon to ſtand in the light, and do hinder the bringing forth of ſome ſuch accurſed birth, according unto the Politick Counſel of <hi>Contzen the Jeſuite,</hi> who exhorts them to take away thoſe that are forward and hot men, Zealous for truth: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Haereſiarchae &amp; doctores errorum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. pellendi ſunt una vice ſi commodè fieri queat, ſin minus, ſenſim &amp; paulatim.</hi> li. 2. Politic. ca. 18. <hi>modus reducendae verae religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis.</hi>
               </note> and then <hi>error</hi> (for ſo he calls truth) <hi>cui patrocinium deerit, ſine pugna concidet:</hi> or at leaſt they being removed, thoſe may be be brought in who are unable either to diſcern truth from error, or to convince the gainſayer, and ſo the <hi>blind leading the blind, both may fall into the Ditch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly, <hi>That general outcry that is upon all Truths, Ordinances and ways of Religion among us, as Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian:</hi> Our <hi>Churches</hi> Antichriſtian, our <hi>Miniſtry</hi> Antichriſtian, our <hi>Laws</hi> Antichriſtian, &amp;c. For it is Satans manner, when he would ſet up Antichriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, to blend all the things of Chriſt, with the Name of Antichriſt; thus giving <hi>the Wine of her Fornication in a golden Cup:</hi> For Antichriſt muſt blaſpheme Gods name, <hi>his Tabernacle, and them that dwell in Heaven:</hi> neither hath this been a late deſign only (for none of the Opinions or Practices that are amongſt us are new) but there was a book written many years ago, Entituled, <hi>Praemonitiones Chriſti &amp; Apoſtolorum, de abolendo Chriſto vero per Antichriſtum:</hi> Wherein the Doctrine of the Trinity, the two natures of Chriſt, his ſuffering in the fleſh, and his ſatisfaction unto God for ſin: All theſe are ſaid to be <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Doctrines, and endeavoured to be cenſured under that Notion of a deſign of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> to undermine the true Chriſt; who, ſaith the Author, is Chriſt in the Spirit, and not in the fleſh:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51309:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> Let none therefore be moved to hear every thing now termed Antichriſtian, whether in Doctrine or practice, according unto the licentiouſneſs of men: but rather fear, leſt under the name of <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> the things of Chriſt be caſt off, &amp; he who is truly Antichriſt brought in, <hi>who comes with all deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tenthly, <hi>When I conſider alſo that general careleſneſs and inadventencie</hi> that is even amongſt the <hi>people of God</hi> concerning theſe things, a <hi>ſpirit of ſlumber</hi> (and it is to be feared in Judgement) being come upon them: ſo that no man mourns under it, no man lays it unto his heart. I can remember when the Doctrines of Arminianiſm were revived in <hi>England</hi> by Mr. <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagues</hi> Book, what impreſſion it made upon the ſpirits of the godly, called then the <hi>Puritans</hi> of this Nation: what mourning, faſting, praying, writing there was againſt it; but now even Godly men ſleep, whilſt the <hi>Enemy</hi> ſows theſe <hi>Tares.</hi> This makes me to ſee need of preſſing this exhortation, that you <hi>come out,</hi> that <hi>you keep out of Babylon.</hi> Oh that the Lord would make it <hi>a Voice from Heaven to you!</hi> For though there be many abominable Hereſies, Sects, and Errors in this Land at this day, and in this City: Yet upon the forementioned grounds, I am enclined to conceive, that they all play <hi>ſmall game</hi> but the Papiſts, who inſinuate themſelves under all theſe Forms; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by intend worſe to us then a Powder plot, if the Lord prevent it not: and I am perſwaded they had <hi>never greater hopes of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> 2. But ſeeing God hath brought us out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> what may we do to keep our ſelves from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning thither again? Here I ſhall offer to you theſe few <hi>Directions,</hi> as Preſervatives.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:51309:19"/>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Receive the truth in the love of it,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.10,11. For this was the cauſe that did provoke God to give men up unto that efficacy of deceit at firſt: Endeavor therefore to know, and to be eſtabliſhed in truth, that you be not carried away with <hi>every wind of Doctrine;</hi> and do not plead for truth, as Lawyers plead cauſes, by other mens evidences, but get an experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental knowledge thereof in your own ſouls: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, it is the great <hi>depoſitum</hi> committed unto you to keep, <hi>Buy it therefore, and ſell it not: contend earneſtly for the faith, claim it as your inheritance for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Let all thoſe that fear God,</hi> unite <hi>againſt this common adverſary:</hi> your diviſions will always be his advantages, their way having always been to fiſh in ſuch troubled waters; <hi>Captare tempor a impacata,</hi> Rev. 15.1. though the <hi>Sea of glaſs</hi> be mingled with <hi>fire,</hi> yet they that have gotten <hi>Victory over the Beaſt,</hi> ſhould ſtand together upon the ſame Sea, with the <hi>Harps of God</hi> in their hands: <hi>Commune periculum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiâ pulſandum.</hi> It is the obſervation of <hi>Bullinger</hi> ſeveral times in his Book <hi>de Perſecut. Eccleſ.</hi> That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the diſſention of Brethren among themſelves, God did give them up into the hands of the Enemy, <hi>ad abſtergendum aeruginem, quae quotidie magis as mag is creſcebat:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Temporibus Aureliani Imperatoris, &amp;c. Chriſtiani optime inter ſe convenie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant: ſed ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens illud fludium im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minutum, diſſentiones auctae ſunt, praecipue inter Epiſcopos &amp; doctores. Ideoque Dominus paſſus eſt infideles Ethnicos manum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae injicere. Ita temporibus Conſtantini, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Yet let not this union be ſinfull, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy: unto that I exhort you not; For <hi>Caſtam Chriſti ſponſum decet caſta concordia:</hi> but you that agree in the <hi>Foundations,</hi> the great things of Religion, though in certain forms you differ, or in truths of leſſer alloy, yet take <hi>Luthers</hi> Counſel to the <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinberg,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:51309:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> to ſilence your diſputes untill a fitter opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>Meum conſilium eſt, ut cauſam hanc ſinatis ad tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ſopitam jacere, hoc tempore enim &amp; animis ſic affectis venenum eſt diſputare.</hi> And be ſure in your diverſity of <hi>opinion,</hi> you endeavor to <hi>keep unity in affection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Suſpect all new Doctrines:</hi> For we are to enquire for the <hi>old way, the good way, that we may find reſt to our ſouls:</hi> we are to go forth <hi>by the ſteps of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient flocks:</hi> Novelty hath always leaven in it the people of God antiently feared not only novel Doctrines or Tenents, but <hi>new coined words,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for with ſuch, falſe teachers uſe to come: <hi>Felix Eccleſin cum nova de Deo dicere laſcivia crederetur;</hi> that Church is in a happy condition when all Novelties in Doctrine are ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be barely the fruit <hi>of wanton wits</hi> and prophane hearts.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Take heed of hearing any of thoſe that would bring in Popiſh leaven:</hi> Your ears are not your own, <hi>take heed what you hear; itching ears</hi> ſeldom conſent to true, but ordinarily to unſound Doctrine, 2 Joh. 10. <hi>If they bring not this Doctrine, receive them not into your houſe, bid them not God-ſpeed:</hi> Thoſe common civilities which unto ſome ſtrangers are a duty, they cannot without ſin be performed towards men that <hi>corrupt truths,</hi> and <hi>hunt ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Let Magiſtrates do their duty</hi> towards Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: It is <hi>Bellarmines</hi> Doctrine, that they are <hi>Religionis defenſores, non Judices:</hi> but you (Right Honorable, with the reſt in Authority) ought to Judge which is the true Religion, and to endeavor to maintain it, Chriſtianity taking in all our relations: and the Lord having promiſed, Iſa. 49.23. <hi>That Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fathers, and Queens thy nurſing Mothers:</hi> that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51309:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> which is promiſed to the Church as a <hi>mercy,</hi> Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſhould make Conſcience to perform as a <hi>duty.</hi> Do you therefore afford favor and encouragement unto thoſe that are good, and be you a terror unto them that are evil: Mark <hi>thoſe that cauſe Diviſions, and raiſe Diſtractions among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>Give unto God the glory of the</hi> mercy of this day: Let your <hi>Vials be gold,</hi> and <hi>full of Odours.</hi> The Enemies fall before the <hi>praiſes,</hi> as well as the <hi>prayers</hi> of Gods people: <hi>Out of the mouths of Babes and Sucklings he hath ordained ſtrength,</hi> Pſal. 8.2. which is rendred by Chriſt, <hi>thou haſt perfected praiſe,</hi> Mat. 21.16. and this ſhall be powerfull, <hi>to ſtill the Enemy and the avenger.</hi> I ſhall conclude all with that, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.22. when they began <hi>to ſing, and to praiſe the Lord, the Lord ſet am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhments againſt the children of</hi> Ammon, Moab, <hi>and</hi> Mounſeir, <hi>that they helped to deſtroy one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51309:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
